<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the right high and mightie prince, Iames by the grace of God, King of great Britannie, France, and Irelande, defender of the faith, &amp;c. An humble supplication for toleration and libertie to enioy and observe the ordinances of Christ Iesus in th'administration of his churches in lieu of humane constitutions.</title>
            <author>Jacob, Henry, 1563-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04219</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843227_7942</idno>
  <idno type="VID">7942</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264190581</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 14339</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S107528</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99843227e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04219)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7942)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 993:10, 2340:8d)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the right high and mightie prince, Iames by the grace of God, King of great Britannie, France, and Irelande, defender of the faith, &amp;c. An humble supplication for toleration and libertie to enioy and observe the ordinances of Christ Iesus in th'administration of his churches in lieu of humane constitutions.</title>
                  <author>Jacob, Henry, 1563-1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Schilders],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Middelburg :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Henry Jacob.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An humble supplication to His Maiestie.</note>
                  <note>This printing has an erratum at the foot of p. 48.</note>
                  <note>The copy of this item at reel 2340:8d is fourth in a group of ten items bound and filmed together.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: copy at reel 2340:8d is damaged, with loss of print on last leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in: British Library (reel 993:10) and Boston Public Library (reel 2340:8d).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Brownists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Religious tolerance --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7942:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7942:1"/>
            <p>To the right High and mightie Prince, <hi>IAMES</hi> by the grace of God, King of great <hi>Britannie, France,</hi> and <hi>Irelande,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the faith, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>An humble Supplication for Toleration and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to enioy and observe the ordinances of Christ IESVS in th'administration of his Churches in lieu of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane constitutions.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 35.11.</bibl>
               <p>Cruell witnesses did rise vp: they asked of me things that I knew not.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.22.</bibl>
               <p>Vnto thee (o King) I haue done no hurt.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 24.14.</bibl>
               <p>But this I confesse vnto thee, that after the way (which they call heresie) so worship I the God of my Fathers, beleeving all things which are written in the Law and in the Prophets.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Tertul. ad Scapul.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Colimus Imperatorem vt hominem a Deo secundum, &amp; solo Deo minorem.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>1609.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:7942:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:7942:2"/>
            <head>To the right High and Mightie Prince, <hi>IAMES</hi> by the grace of God, King of great Britannie, France and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. An humble <hi>Supplication</hi> for a Toleration and libertie to enjoy and obserue the ordinances of Christ Iesus in the administration of his churches in lieu of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane constitutions.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Most gratious Soveraigne and mightie Prince,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving observed on th'one parte your Maiesties Princely inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to distribute iustice and mercie amongst your people, and called to mind on the other parte the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest we have, as being your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, to the worthie comforts &amp; advantages which the King of Kings hath inclosed in your Royall Scepter, that you might deliver them foorth &amp; dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose them according to the occasions presented: We your High. faithful servants the silēced and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced Ministers of the Gospel, together with sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie others concurring in opinion and persuasion of religion with vs, do in all humilitie presume to make tender vnto your Ma. of an humble motion, such as concerneth the glorie of Christs Kingdome, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7942:3"/>of your Imperial Crowne, the service of the Churches amongst vs, and the particular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of vs the said Ministers and people in this time of our extraordinarie distresse. To the offer where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee have the rather imboldned our selfes, in that wee have out of your gracious proceedinges to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards some of a Romish &amp; disaffected spirit discer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a great and comfortable presumption, that it shalbe lawfull for each loyall and religious subiect without preiudice to his life or libertie, not only to sigh at home in the case of publike and private grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, but (so farre as it may be done with all dew regarde and reverence) to crye also by way of Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication in the eare of his Prince: who will (we do not doubt) out of an honorable respect to iustice, take notice of the weightie motions offered by his people: and whose sacred persone wee hope th'Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie hath reserved and designed to be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per meane and instrument, not only of further esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment, protection and beautie to the Churches amongst vs, but also of a final ruine to that Dagon of Rome, and to all the appendants &amp; pompe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Wee acknowledge you are the Lords Lieu-te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent: wee finde you haue such care of matters ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, that you proceede in the managing of the same according to the commission you haue received from so high and glorious a Maiestie. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee can not otherwise apprehend but that you will performe the like in the cause of the Lords spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Kingdome: wherein if you shall answereably
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7942:3"/>to the addresse and instructions you haue from him sway your royal Scepter, and approve vnto him and to the people vnder your charge, that your care in this behalfe is so much the greater, by how much heaven is to be prized above earth, immortalitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mortalitie, and the power of the spirit aboue all excellencie of the flesh: your Ma: shall greatly honour your selfe in the eye of your people, and establish the throne you sit on: so as neither your enemies shall adventure to attempt or plot ought against it, nor your most noble issue feare any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment or disturbance therein.</p>
            <p>Vnder this hope of a gracious acceptatiō on your Ma: parte, and withall out of a perswasion of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of the cause we pleade for (we resting as yet vnconvinced by the Prelates of any error) and out of a conscience of the integritie and dutiefulnes of our hearts to your High.<note place="margin">Witnes the offer of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputat. and other boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>answered.</note> having never intertained or harboured in them the least spark of<note n="*" place="margin">My L. of Salisburie in his answ. to certaine scā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal. papers.</note> disloyaltie to your Persone &amp; Crowne; we prostrate our selves at your High. feete, most humbly intreating, That whereas the <hi>Prelates,</hi> our professed adversaries, and their officers, have not either for the nature of their offices, or for the qualitie of their proceedings any warrant from the word of the Lord IESVS, or the lawes of this Kingdome (as we, in case your Ma: shall vouchsafe vs audience, are readie to iustifie) your Ma: would bee pleased that wee the saide Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters and others may for the considerations here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after mentioned, have allowed vnto vs by way of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7942:4"/>
               <hi>Toleration. First,</hi> the libertie of enioying and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the holy ordinances enacted and left by the Lord for the perpetual direction and guiding of his Churches. <hi>Secondly,</hi> an entier exemption from the iurisdiction of the said Prelates and their officers. And <hi>lastly,</hi> this happines to live vnder the cōmaund &amp; charge of any your subordinate civill Magistrats, and so to be for our actions and cariage in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie accomptable vnto them, and likewise liable vnto all such duties and taxations, as are by the law and custome of this lande in any sort chargeable v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon subiectes of our calling and condition.</p>
            <p>The considerations that may induce your Ma: to yeeld vs satisfaction herein, are in summe these. <hi>First,</hi> in that the church-governement solicited by vs, is more compatible with your Imperiall Scepter and more advantageable thereto, then that of the said Prelates. <hi>Secondly,</hi> in that it standeth with the policie and reason of State to allow the Toleration and exemption desired by vs. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> in that the courses held by the said Prelates against vs, are for the extreeme rigour and partialitie of them such, as your Ma: vpon dew information received, cannot but in iustice and commiseration affoord vs reliefe and redresse.</p>
            <p>Touching the first consideration, viz. <hi>That the Church-governement</hi> sollicited by vs doth better sure with your Imperiall Scepter, and is of greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage thereto, then that of the Prelats. The truth hereof will appeare vnto your Ma: in case you shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be pleased to take knowledge in particular of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7942:4"/>opinions and proceedings helde by the <hi>Prelats</hi> of this your Realme on the one side, and by vs the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners</hi> for the said Toleration on the other.</p>
            <p>Whereas the State of England is free, intier and independent, holding immediatly from the Lorde of heaven each office and ministerie aswell in the Churches as the Common-wealth, &amp; not deriving it, either in whole or in parte, frō any forreine Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate &amp; Governour on earth. It may please your Ma. to examine, whether <hi>Wee,</hi> your most humble Petitioners (who avow and professe that wee have and ought to have our whole spirituall office and power of administration at home and from among our selves) doe herein preiudice the saide free and independent State of England, or the <hi>Prelats,</hi> who hold their office and ministerle to be essentially de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived and conferred vpon them not by any autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie domesticall and proper to the State, but by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of such ordination as was cōveyed to their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors from the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Wherein as the saide Prelats doe cast an apparent blemish and dishonour vpon the Gospell professed by your Ma. and your people, as if from and by the meanes of Antichrist, the Churches of Christ should receive the assurance and warrant of their ministerie, and cōsequently of their faith and celestiall inheritance: so doe they in this particular disclayme the sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine absolutenes and independencie of the State wherin they live, and make both your Maiestie and them selves tyed, in regard of their said ministerie so received, to acknowledge some obligation and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7942:5"/>to the sea of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> We not finding either in the doctrine propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Gospel, or in the practise observed by the Apostles in the churches planted by them, any war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for Provinciall or Diocesan Bishops, doe hold their function and calling to be meere humane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions; and therefore that it is in your Maiesties power to remove them from out your Dominions, and to confine them to <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Toledo.</hi> And this was the iudgement of the Prelates and Clergie in the dayes of King Henrie the 8. as may appeare by a Treatise intituled, <hi>The institution of a Christian man,</hi> published and dedicated to the said King. This also was the opinion of this whole <hi>State</hi> in the time of <hi>K. Edw. 6.</hi> and since of the late most worthie <hi>Queene:</hi> yea of <hi>Archbishop</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Preface pag. 2 et pa. 8<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>17. 372</note>
               <hi>Whitegift</hi> likewise, and <hi>R. Hooker,</hi> who spared not to divulge and notifie so much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world.<note n="b" place="margin">Pag 133. 136. 139. 154. 155. 156. 159. 165.</note> Herevnto doe subscribe the best re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed churches in <hi>Europe.</hi> But our Prelates on the contrarie, vnder pretext of deriving the title and birth of their functions and dignities from Christ and his Apostles, by the interposing of the Pope &amp; church of Rome, doe absolutely denie vnto your Ma. the saide power: and so abridging you in an high point of your supremacie, doe intercept and defalke a <hi>prerogative</hi> annexed to your Crowne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Wheras we the said Ministers holde, that the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates both Provinciall and Diocesan ought (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the<note n="c" place="margin">1. Eward. 6. cap. 12. Item anno. 1. Iacobi. cap. 25.</note> Statutes provided in that behalfe) to derive by vertue of Letters pattents, their Episcopal iurisdiction and authoritie of keeping Courtes and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7942:5"/>sending forth processe from and in the name, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the seale of armes of your Highnes and Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors: they, the said Prelates, on the contrarie have recourse to Provinciall and Diocesan Deanes and Chapters for this their imploymēt: and do in their owne names keepe Courtes, sende foorth processe, and execute other partes of iurisdiction ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call: wherein whether they incoūter not your Ma. Soveraintie, Prerogative and Lawes, wee humbly leave vnto you to be considered.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> We the said Ministers take it as a certaine &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controlable Maxime, that it resteth in your Ma. to dispose of the temporalities of the Church. This was the iudgement of that worthie <hi>Iohn</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Wals hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor. R. 2.</note>
               <hi>Wickliffe.</hi> And the <hi>Emperour Frederick</hi> could say:<note n="b" place="margin">Catal. test. Veritat. in Frederic.</note>
               <hi>Aufera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus illis nocen tes divitias: hoc enim facere, est opus cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis.</hi> For the doing wherof, he may seeme to haue received incouragement frō<note n="c" place="margin">Ambros. contra. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xent.</note>
               <hi>Ambrose,</hi> who appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth this course, and from a certen<note n="d" place="margin">Decret p. 2. caus. 11. Q 1. c. 27.</note> canon agreeing in iudgement with <hi>Ambrose.</hi> But the said<note n="e" place="margin">Admonit against Mar tin Marpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat.</note> Prelates accompting it a piece of Sacriledge to have drawen and resumed from them &amp; their state what hath bin conferred vpon them, will not allowe vnto your Ma: this regall power.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> We the said Ministers keepe our selves within the limites of our function Ecclesiasticall, wholy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing all publique civill offices and governement: whereas the Prelates, disbanding them selves, as it were, from out the compasse assigned vnto them, doe rancke their persons with, and before temporall Lords: and ioyne in commission for the managing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7942:6"/>of State affaires with the Nobilitie and Gentrie of the Realme: so farre foorth as they make no scruple and difficultie to professe, that in case by your Ma. and the State they should be discharged and seclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from all Civil power and office as persons inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable thereof, you should thereby doe vnto them a manifest wrong, and expose the Church to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarde of ruine. Wherein as they greatly preiudice your Imperial Crowne: so they offer no meane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignitie and iniurie to the temporal State, by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting and feazing vpon the Magistracie &amp; char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which are the proper right and interest of the Nobilitie and Gentrie: and doe likewise worke an extraordinarie impeachement and hurt to the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique good of your High. person, governement &amp; kingdome, by withdrawing their personall indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and cares from informing your subiects in the dueties of obedience, to God and your Ma.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> We hold that all Officers and Ministers of the Gospel ought to be subject to your High. and to all and everie your subordinate civill Magistrates. And that the civil Magistrates <hi>only</hi> ought to be the <hi>Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seers</hi> of Provinces and Dioceses, and of the severall Churches therein: And that it is a dutie enioyned them by God, and which your Ma. should by way of commission impose vpon the Nobilitie &amp; Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie in the severall Counties of your Kingdome, namely to sit in commission, and to take notice of al mis-government in persons Ecclesiastique, cōmitted either in the course of their life, or teaching: and so to proceede accordingly to censure &amp; redresse. But
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7942:6"/>the Prelates will not allow vnto your Ma. this point of Regall supremacie: they cannot thus subiect and abase themselves. They must be, some of them great <hi>Primates:</hi> some <hi>Countie Palatines:</hi> most of them <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners for the peace:</hi> al of them of an eminent au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie &amp; power within their proper Dioceses: so as for persons of their rancke &amp; qualitie to be subiect to the proceedings and censure of such, as in everie severall Countie carie the sword and authoritie ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill vnder your Ma: is held by them no lesse intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, then for a Counseler of State to be subiect to a pettie <hi>Constable</hi> or <hi>Borsholder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> As we holde that your Ma. within your Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions hath power to cal <hi>Synods</hi> &amp; to dissolve them: so we hold likewise that ruling Synods and vnited Presbyteries exercising government and imposing Lawes &amp; Decrees vpon severall Churches, and the Pastors of them, are not onely humane institutions, but in regarde of the said governement and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of imposing lawes, altogether vnlawfull, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surping vpon the Supremacie of the civill. Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate,<note place="margin">Protest. of the Kings Suprem. pag. 4. sect. 8.</note> in whose power only it resteth to enact &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deine lawes ecclesiasticall for and over all the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches within his Dominions. And therefore they are not desired by vs as a meane either to curbe &amp; force the civill Magistrate (a course abhorred by vs, and vtterly repugnant to our profession and practise) or to procure countenance and respect to our ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall function amongst others. We acknowledge (as hath bin above remembred) no other power &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie for the overseeing, ruling and censuring of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7942:7"/>particular Churches (how many soever in number) in the case of their misgovernement, thē that which is originally invested in your Royall person, &amp; from it derived to such of your laitie, as you shall iudge worthie to be deputed to the execution of the same vnder you. So as the favour humbly sollicited by vs, is, that whereas our Lord Iesus hath givē to each particular church or ordinarie congregation this right and priviledge, viz. to elect, ordeine, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive her owne Ministers, and to exercise all other partes of lawful ecclesiasticall iurisdictiō vnder him, your Ma. would be pleased to take order aswell that each particular church, that shalbe allowed to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in the benefite of the said Toleratiō, may haue, enioy, and put in execution and practise this her said right and priviledge: as that some your subalterne civill officers may be appointed by you to demand and receive of each church a dew and iust accompt of their proceedings. <hi>Here</hi> we doe humbly, intreat that we may not be so interpreted as if wee disclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all sortes of Synods. It is the <hi>ruling</hi> and not the <hi>deliberative</hi> and <hi>persuasive Synode</hi> which wee except against. That a Synode should inioyne vs to receive and intertaine a cōstitution inacted by them selves, we hold it vnlawfull. To be moved thereto by way of persuasion grounded vpon a cleare demonstrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of vtilitie and advantage growing thereby to the churches, we doe in no sorte dislike. How farre in this question of Synods, the Prelates doe dissent frō vs, both touching opinion and practise, it cannot be vnknowen to any, who are in any measure acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7942:7"/>with the cariage of church affaires. They, the said Prelates for the<note n="a" place="margin">Whitegift pag. 436.</note> calling of Synodes mainteine the necessitie of the office of an Archbishop:<note n="b" place="margin">Bish. of Lincol. in his answ. to a catho. pag. 170.</note> they assume to them selves the power of enacting lawes: and leave to your Ma. a <hi>bare</hi> commaund for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of them. The Synods held by them are of a large extent: their authoritie reaching from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beersheba,</hi> frō <hi>Dover</hi> in <hi>Kent</hi> to the <hi>Mount</hi> in <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall:</hi> and are withall of such power and readie exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, as where their Canons and Decrees encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contradiction, there they proceed to the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mest censures. They imploy their apparitors to cite and commaunde appearance; they imprison: they deprive: they degrade: they excommunicate: they anathematize. Here we appeale to your Ma. hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beseeching you to consider, whether the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, whose spirituall arme is of an exorbitant strength, and reaching from the <hi>East</hi> of your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the <hi>West</hi> thereof, and is able in sort to curb your <hi>Nobilitie</hi> and <hi>Gentrie:</hi> or <hi>wee</hi> the Ministers sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciting reformation, whose power is boūded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the limites of a poore parishe, and subiect to the authoritie and controlement of any your meanest Commissioners for the peace, doe exercise a iuris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and governement most compatible with your imperiall Scepter. It may please you to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and weigh in your Princely apprehensions &amp; thoughtes, to whom the title and name of <hi>Pope</hi> (so often obiected by our adversaries to a <hi>Parish pastor</hi>) may with best reason be appropriated, whether to a poore Minister (who of him selfe and without assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7942:8"/>from others, standeth disabled for matter of iurisdiction, and when he hath out of a cōcurrence from his Collegues with him an authoritie to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed iudicially, yet cannot make it obligatorie &amp; of validitie otherwise then with the cōsent and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the proper precincts of his particular congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) or to a <hi>Prelate,</hi> who ruleth alone without check, and whose power of iurisdiction is not onely spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual but also <hi>civil:</hi> and not confined to a Parish but extended to whole Dioceses &amp; Provinces. If your Ma. shal thinke meete for the clearing of this point of the appropriation of the title and name of <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>popeling,</hi> to relye vpon the iudgement of your greatest Prelates, you may readily be satisfied and resolved herein. For they haue by the mouth of D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Downame</hi> preaching at <hi>Lambeth</hi> in favour and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Episcopall preheminence and authoritie concluded, and since <hi>cum privilegio</hi> vnder speciall allowance divulged &amp; recommended to the world this theologicall and vndoubted Maxime, viz. <hi>That a Minister having supreme and sole authoritie in the Church and causes ecclesiasticall, or ruling alone without controlement, &amp; not subiected to the authoritie of a Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesan or Provinciall Bishop, ruleth as a Pope.</hi> The ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of this Maxime we humbly leave to your Maiestie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> whereas by their Canons they crosse the equall and proportionable distributiō of iustice en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned by the lawes of the Land, in that they cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure some enormous crimes lightly, and impose a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere punishment on some cariage that in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7942:8"/>of the lawes of God &amp; of this Realme, either runneth not in the accompt of a crime, or is in the nature of a light transgression. And whereas by the 53. <hi>Canon</hi> they take frō the subiect the libertie gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him by law divine and humane to deliver his opinion in a controverted point of Religion: and likewise by another<note n="a" place="margin">Canon 98</note> Canon all benefite of appeale allowed by the Lawes of this Kingdome. And whereas also they excommunicate such as<note n="b" place="margin">Canon 139.</note> denie the <hi>Convocation</hi> to be the representative Church of the true churches of God within Englande, which said churches are in the true sense and intendement of our lawes iudged to consist not only of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie but of the <hi>King,</hi> Nobilitie and Commons: wee doe in all hum litie beseech your Ma. to consider, whether the said Prelats doe in these severall points proceed with dew regarde vnto your Ma. and the State.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now</hi> forasmuch as the saide Prelats, <hi>By</hi> deriving their office and ministerie from the forrein power of the church of <hi>Rome: By</hi> denying vnto your Ma: the authoritie of removing &amp; abrogating the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Diocesan and Provinciall Bishops: <hi>By</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting iurisdictiō Episcopall in their owne names, and vnder their owne Seale of armes, contrarie to the expresse letter of the Statutes provided in that behalf: <hi>By</hi> accompting it sacriledge that your High should by your regall authoritie dispose of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralties of the church: <hi>By</hi> vsurping and managing civill offices, and so withdrawing them selves from informing your Subiects in the dueties of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7942:9"/>to God and your Ma: <hi>By</hi> exempting their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, in regard of their eminent dignitie and charge both in church and common wealth, from vnder the iurisdiction and power of your subordinate ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Magistrats: <hi>By</hi> drawing into vse ruling Synods, such namely as whose power is extendable to the vtmost confines of this your Kingdome, and over such your Subiects, as are aswell of a Noble ranke and qualitie, as of a meane degree and condition: <hi>By</hi> taking and assuming to them selves the power of enacting lawes ecclesiasticall, &amp; leaving to your Ma. a <hi>bare</hi> commande only to see them executed. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as the saide Prelats doe, by these their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings grounded vpon opinions in them answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thereto, not a litle disadvantage your Ma. in the point of your regall power and soveraintie: <hi>We</hi> doe in al humblenes intreate that the consideration hereof may pleade with your High. in favour of vs the said Ministers, who neither hold in opinion nor intertaine in practise any matter either preiudiciall to your royall State, Supremacie and Prerogatives (as our Adversaries doe) or pertaking of Confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on growing from the roote of that accursed <hi>paritie,</hi> which incoūtreth the <hi>subordinatiō</hi> of officers, which we, agreeably to the word of trueth, doe mainteine to be of as necessarie and worthie vse in the body of Christ, as in a body naturall: in which all mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are not eyes, or heades or handes, but one is an <hi>heade,</hi> another is an <hi>hande,</hi> &amp;c. so in the body of Christ one is <hi>Pastor,</hi> another <hi>Teacher,</hi> others <hi>Elders,</hi> others <hi>Deacons,</hi> &amp;c. And yet we disclayme not such
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7942:9"/>equalitie as betwixt distinct and separate churches the Spirit of all wisedome hath instituted &amp; recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended: it being in them, as they are with respect of the one to the other considered, no more an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruitie or disproportion, then parity in eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and power betwixt the several Kings and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>Europe.</hi> As it would be a matter of infinite harshnes and of perillous sequele to sovereine Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, if one amongst them should seaze vpon the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar soveraintie of each, and so intercept that pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in Scepter and governement, which the <hi>Prince of Princes</hi> hath betwixt them respectiuely ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: so can it not succeed otherwise in the case of distinct churches, when that power, which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to each by divine institution, shalbe transferred and linked vpon one. This Primacie in power of one Pastor and Church over the rest in the same Kingdome, would (where there be of <hi>Arch prelats</hi> sundrie and distinct Seas) be hardly with patience endured by them. With vs the Arch-prelats of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> and <hi>Yorke:</hi> in France of <hi>Rhemes</hi> and <hi>Lyons:</hi> in Germany of <hi>Coleyn</hi> and <hi>Mentz,</hi> can well brooke <hi>some</hi> subiection to their severall Princes. But a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination of <hi>Yorke</hi> to <hi>Canterburie,</hi> of <hi>Rhems</hi> to <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> of <hi>Coleyn</hi> to <hi>Mentz,</hi> would happely prove in the stomacks of deintie Prelats a matter of such crudity and indigestion, as that <hi>Subordination</hi> would bee held by them the mother of Confusion and <hi>Paritie</hi> magnified as the authour of excellent beautie and grace in the church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For a further inducement</hi> to your Ma. in this behalf,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7942:10"/>we are bold to adde herevnto, that it standeth with Policie and reason of State to allowe the Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and exemption desired by vs. But here wee doe humbly beseech your Ma. not to thinke that by our sute for the said <hi>Toleration</hi> wee make an ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verture and way for Toleration vnto Papistes, our Sute being of a different nature from theirs, and the inducements therof such, as cannot cōclude ought in favour of them, whose <hi>head</hi> is <hi>Antichrist:</hi> whose <hi>worshippe</hi> is <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> whose doctrine is <hi>heresie,</hi> and a <hi>profession</hi> directly contrarie to the lawfull State and Governement of free Countries and Kingdomes, as your Ma. hath <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>iudiciously</hi> observed. As we doe not herein give advantage vnto Papistes, so doe wee not by way of <hi>Separation</hi> disclay me com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with such Churches amongst vs, as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of Ecclesiasticall regiment differ from vs: being readie to communicate with them in the Lords worship, when without personall and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie participation in sinne, wee may doe the same. For your satisfaction then in this point, vouchsafe vs <hi>(most mightie and noble Prince)</hi> this princely equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and patiēce, as to be informed of that which we doe here present.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>May</hi> it therefore please your Ma. in the first place to be remēbred, that it is sutable with the wise pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of worthie Kings for the reducing of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialities &amp; troubles in their States to a peaceable is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue, to draw into practise that expedient and meane, which former experiēce hath proved to be of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie vse to this purpose. If a Prince should make que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7942:10"/>hereof: the <hi>Physiciā</hi> &amp; <hi>Navigator</hi> could resolve him herein: the one is in his cure, the other in say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ever holding that course, which observation &amp; trial hath discovered to be fit and serviceable to the endes they ayme at. That the said Toleration is for pacifying contentions in the matter of religiō pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed by vs a readie meane, may appeare hereby, in that it removeth both the original cause &amp; nourish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof: &amp; in that it hath been for this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent service intertained by great Monarchs and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentats both in ancient times &amp; of late yeres. Vpon this ground did the Romane Empetours surcease their persecution of the Christians, granting vnto thē the libertie not only to serve the Lord Iesus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the holy Ordinances prescribed by him, but to erect also for the better accōplishment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of convenient buildings &amp; places. Vpon this groūd did <hi>Athenagoras</hi> in his Apologie, persuade the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Commodus</hi> thereto. There hath not yet pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed much more then halfe an age, since <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, a Prince of deepe &amp; politike reach, permitted vnto those in Germanie (whom hee had for the cause of Religion pursued with armes) as the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test meane of pacification, the free vse of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession embraced by them. Herein was <hi>Charles</hi> a worthie patterne and precedent to <hi>Maximilian</hi> the <hi>Emperour,</hi> who at <hi>Vienna,</hi> and in the Cities descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto him by inheritance, was out of the rule of Policie, well pleased to yeelde intertaynement to that Religion, which himselfe regarded not. It is knowen to sundrie yet living, that the French
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7942:11"/>King <hi>Henrie</hi> the third, when he was to receive the Crowne of <hi>Poland,</hi> notwithstāding his zeale to the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> condescended to the observation and practise in that Kingdome, of the whole do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine propounded in the writings of the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listes and Apostles.<note place="margin">Comment de stat. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. &amp; Reip. sub Henr. 3.5. part. lib. 14.</note> In the time of the said <hi>Henry</hi> the third, when the Prince of <hi>Condy</hi> and other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants of note and dignitie confederate with him, became suters for Toleration of Religiō, it is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be considered what course was helde by <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel</hi> Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> being drawen to mediate with the said King in furtherāce of the Protestants sute. Though he, the said Duke, acknowledged all service and devotion to that Romish and Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Sea, yet in the instructions delivered by him to his servant <hi>Molarius,</hi> whom for the purpose afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said he addressed into <hi>France,</hi> hee expresly charged him to pleade with all earnestnes for the grant of Toleration to the Protestants: and not only to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde vnto the King the exemple of the course held by him the said Prince for tolerating the intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction and exercise of Religion in sundrie parts of <hi>Savoy,</hi> but likewise to advertise him of the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and good succes he, the saide Duke, had in his particular experience discerned and founde of the Toleration allowed by him. And not satisfied here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, he further enjoyned <hi>Molarius</hi> to treate in all se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious maner with the Embassadours sent from the popish Cantons in <hi>Zuitserland,</hi> that they likewise would vrge and recōmend vnto the French King the cause of Toleration. At the same time it pleased
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7942:11"/>the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of happy memorie by her Ambassador D. <hi>Dale,</hi> to negotiate with the said King a pacification in the behalf of the Protestants, and to presse, as a special and worthy remedy of the present troubles, a grant on the Kings parte of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for thē to professe in publique &amp; with securitie to their persons, honors &amp; goods the Religion liked and followed by them. This course of Toleration is held by <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth now reigning in <hi>France:</hi> by the present Emperour in divers parts of his Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories: by the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and allowed off by the <hi>Spaniard</hi> in his late Treatie with the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> and other the vnited Provinces. The liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Gospell and the free exercise of every part thereof both for <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Governement,</hi> is obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be of so <hi>harmeles</hi> &amp; <hi>peaceable</hi> a nature and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and so farr from <hi>wronging</hi> any Monarch in his Soveraintie and publike interest, that the very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, the <hi>Persian</hi> namely and the <hi>Turke,</hi> give passage and entertainement therevnto. What advantage the Princes above named doe receive therby, to the assuring of their Scepters, and to the advancement of the common good and honor of their estates: the same <hi>(O mightie Prince)</hi> may your Maiest. reape with the addition of a great glory to your person.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As the grant of <hi>Toleration</hi> persuaded by vs, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with this vnvaluable effect of giving end to Controversies and Dissentions in a State, such as issue from difference in opinion touching points of our Religion: so in case your Ma. shall bee pleased to condescend therevnto, it will bee found
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7942:12"/>not vnworthie the intertayning for matter of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie.</hi> For whereas the Prelats by their Courts &amp; their Officers and such proceedings as they observe likewise in private, doe yeerely, without all warrant from the word of God, drawe from the Subiect no lesse a proportion then a <hi>Subsidie</hi> or two amounteth vnto, and so disable the Subiect to furnish the ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>narie payments &amp; contributions of State: if it shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be iudged meet by your High. to honor the people vnder your governement with so gracious a privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as that so many of thē, as relish the <hi>Reformatiō</hi> vrged by vs, may be exempted frō the power of the <hi>Rochet</hi> and <hi>Crozier,</hi> and allowed to live vnder the Governement and holy ordinances of the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, which will and ought to be in each parte of the Kingdome freely and without charge administred to the people: it will fall out that how much is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falked and withdrawen from the Courts of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats, and intercepted from the fingers of their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, so much is reserved in the purse of the Subiect, whereby to inhable him for your Ma: service. Of what advantage and consequence this may grow to be to your imperiall Crowne and dignitie, and of what cōfort and satisfaction to your people now a long time <hi>harassed</hi> &amp; wearied by <hi>Chancellors, Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>missaries, Arch-deacons, Apparitors,</hi> and others of this Trade and Mysterie, we humbly pray to bee exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>Further,</hi> we doe in all submissive sorte beseech your Ma. to call to minde &amp; to weigh in your most wise and grave Deliberations, whether it bee not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7942:12"/>agreeable with the rule of sound Policie, that each Cōstitution and established order in a State should sorte &amp; corresponde with the nature and dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the people living therein. The greatest <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes</hi> have ever held it for a principle vndoubted &amp; observeable. If your Ma. likewise shal so apprehend therof: may it please you thē to consider what cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondence the Canons and Constitutions <hi>Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficall</hi> now in force against vs the saide Ministers and others your loyall Subiects, have with the nature &amp; qualitie of a great parte of the people within the Churches of Englande. It is not vnknowen that partly by the powerfull ministerie of the Gospell, partly by the Plots and attempts on the parte of the <hi>Romanists</hi> for supplanting the Gospell and the Professors thereof, many thousands of your people are wrought to a speciall distaste of such Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Orders of the Prelats, whereby both the faithfull Ministers of the Gospell are in all disgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive and vnworthy sorte (in regarde of their Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie to <hi>Popish</hi> rites and ceremonies) discarded and removed from being any longer the Lords <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinels</hi> and <hi>Watchmen:</hi> and the people also either for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to honor and approve by their presence &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise some the Devises and Institutions of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish Synagogue, left amongst vs in the worship of the Lord, or drawen into question in the case of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusall to their extraordinarie trouble and expense. If then to no meane a multitude of your most du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and loving Subiects the saide Constitutions and Canons be for the respects above mentioned,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7942:13"/>as a <hi>Dose of wormewood</hi> and <hi>gall: Wee</hi> beseech you in your royall wisedome to consider, whether it sute not with the reason of State to limite and restreyne the execution of them, and so to regarde your peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that they may be discharged of al obligation on this behalfe, and allowed in the service of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, not to borrow ought from their sworne &amp; capitall Adversaries the Idolaters of <hi>Rome,</hi> but to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terteyne the ordinances enacted by <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>And</hi> whereas a <hi>Prince</hi> is, by vertue of his regall function and office, tyed to distribute in equall and proportionable sorte the testimonies of his love &amp; care to the good of his people: it may please your Ma. to debate with your royall self. <hi>First</hi> whether it stande with the received Axiomes of Policie, to yeeld respect, countenance &amp; support to one parte of your people vnder your governement, and to suffer the other (who is no lesse, if not more loyall then the former, and whose indeavours have been and are of excellent vse and service for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Gospell) to rest exposed to vnmercifull censure and disgrace. And <hi>secondly,</hi> whether a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of this nature and vpon this grounde of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformitie with Rome in her outwarde and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial cariage, accompanied with a reproach in an high degree, wil not disaffect &amp; discourage the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect (which in all hearty and affectionate sorte wee desire of the Lord, may never happen) though not in the point of loyaltie, yet in the cheerful course of duetie to his <hi>Prince.</hi> If now your Ma. shall dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7942:13"/>that the saide proceeding may thorough the continuance thereof, fall out (which we trust shall never, and pray that it may not) to be of speciall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience and disadvantage vnto you in regard of the said discouragement and disaffection it may raise in the hearts of some your people: And that it is an error in Policie for a Prince to carie an vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable and partiall hande towards those, who in matters which concerne the Gospel &amp; the Lords worship, are equally to cōmunicate in the Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations and pleadges of his favour. It may then please your excellent Ma. (if you finde it to be your owne cafe) to <hi>deliberate</hi> of redresse in this behalfe: and to affoorde the <hi>Lord</hi> that honor, your <hi>selfe</hi> that right, your <hi>people</hi> that contentement and comfort, as to confine and limite the iurisdiction of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats, that it extend not to those who approove Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, but that they may in the service of the Lord Iesus be suffered to observe the Orders and Constitutions enacted by him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <hi>Moreover,</hi> if no reason of State will allow the continuance of that course, which is specially affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and liked by our extreemest enemies, as being of great advantage vnto them in the perill and hurt it worketh to the Churches of this Kingdome and to the profession of the Gospell imbraced by them. And if common sense and experience will advertise vs, that the intertayning of those proceedings and practises, which are most distasted by our adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries as being readie meanes to frustrate their hopes, will best assure vs against their proiects &amp; designes:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7942:14"/>then we presume your Ma. will call to minde how much it importeth you both to commaund a <hi>sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cease</hi> on the Prelats parte of executing their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in the silencing and deprivatiō of their fellow-servaunts the faithfull Ministers of the Gospell: and likewise to take order that the reliques of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ, which have given life &amp; grouth to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alities and factions amongst vs, being displanted, &amp; removed, the holy Ordinances only of our blessed Redeemer and King may by way of <hi>Toleration</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive passage and admittance into some Churches to be gathered by your Ma: speciall grace in some partes of this Kingdome. <hi>That</hi> the course helde by the Prelats against Reformation and the Ministers vrging the same, is of an excellent relish in the taste of the Papists, as the Papists them selves wil readily acknowledge: so the particulating of the effects is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing thereon will evidently cōvince. What is more pleasing and of greater contentement to a Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nist, then the disgracing and silencing of him, who laboureth the subversion of the Doctrine and Sea of <hi>Rome?</hi> When he shall withall discerne that by occasiō of the said Course, many Students of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie parts, doe stay and divert them selves from im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment in the Ministerie: that there is nourished and fed in Romish Catholikes at home and abroad a speciall hope of restoring Poperie to her former reputation amongst vs: that there is raised much splene betwixt the Laborers in the Lords harvest, much harshenes betwixt the severall favorers of either opinion, much disorder and dissolution of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7942:14"/>life: that there is an opportunitie presented vnto Priests and Iesuits for passage hether, and to nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate a reconcilement to the Church of Rome: whē a <hi>Romanist</hi> (I say) shall discerne this effect and issue of the saide course <hi>Pontificall,</hi> will it not cheere and refresh his danted spirits? will it not occasion him to chant a <hi>Te Deum</hi> in regard thereof? That the course solicited by vs the said Ministers is detested by the Romanists, and that it is able to furnish vnto a Prince the meanes of disappointing their hopes, and of securing his State against their plots and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, if it needed for the evidencing thereof anie further Discourse: we could not onely cleare it, by laying forth the admirable power and fruits of the Lords sacred Ordinances practised in forme &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as is prescribed in the worde, but verifie it also out of exemple and experience. If wee should by way of instance name onely vnto your Ma. your Kingdomes of England and Scotland, none know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth so exactly as your noble selfe the malice concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Romanists against the Gospell and the secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie yeelded to your person &amp; Crowne by the free and sincere exercise thereof.</p>
            <p>Seeing then the free exercise of the Gospell, in sorte as is desired, is a meane to assure your Scepter imperiall against the conspiracies of your capitall &amp; greatest Adversaries, the Admirers of that romane <hi>Arch-Priest</hi> and his triple Crowne: And sith the said course held by the Bishops is in regard aswell of the manifold hurtes growing thereby to the Churches of this Realme, as of the sundrie advantages rising
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7942:15"/>therefrom to the Synagogue of Rome, exceedingly approoved and affected by your saide Adversaries: we hope your Ma. will call into deliberation this worthie Admonition: <hi>Neque tuae occasioni desis, neque suam hostides:</hi> and so resolve to give vs contentment in this our iust Sute.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For</hi> your Maiesties further inducement where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, let it not be vnpleasing vnto you to haue it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented to your memorie, that where there bee two factions, the weakning of the one is the streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening of the other. <hi>There</hi> is within this your Kingdome a faction of Romanists: for Number, Strength, Dependancie at home and abroad not to be contemned: for Watchfulnes and Readines to take the advantage of all occurrents and tymes, not vnworthy to be carefully eyed and observed: for Malice to the Gospell and the Professors thereof, vnsatiable: for Desire &amp; secret indeavour to reesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish the authoritie of <hi>S</hi>
               <seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Peters</hi> chaire amongst vs, most affectionate. Now this faction can not but grow so much the more renforced and potent, by how much the Protestant party shalbe infeebled, &amp; lessened. And the Protestant party can not but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minish and languish, in case the aforesaid course of the Prelats be continued. For what hindereth the gaining of great numbers to the side of the Gospel, that must of necessitie impaire and distrengthen the same side. If it shalbe in favour of the Prelats repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that no action can lye against them for any such regarde of hinderāce given to the winning and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of any to the church. It may please your Ma.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7942:15"/>to remēber, that when the ordinarie meane fayleth of gaining to the true Churches of Christ, the act of gaining numbers thereto must determine: but by pursuing the course <hi>Pontificall</hi> aforesaid, the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie meane of cōversion from Blindnes and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie to the Knowledge and Faith of the Gospel is and hath bin interrupted and crossed: not onely in that humane ordinances in the Lords worship receive speciall intertainement amongst vs, and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie</hi> findeth favour for venting and dispersing her infection in discourses from abroad, &amp; in Sermons sometimes from our <hi>Pulpits</hi> at home, but likewise in that so many worthy <hi>Lights</hi> have thereby been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from shining in the Church, so many able and well qualified Students discouraged from hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding place and office therein, so many of good wit and spirit kept from the Vniversitie and disposed of to mechanicall imployments, and so many fitter to labour in the vineyards of <hi>Gascoine,</hi> then in the harvest of the Lord, obtruded to the church. For <hi>in turbis etiam prauus sortitur honorem: &amp; quam digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis sedem quieta repub. desperat, eam perturbata se con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequi posse arbitratur.</hi> If then the said course Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call worke in the party imbracing the Gospell a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of strength, and consequently a further vigour and spirit in the opposite faction: we hope it wilbe iudged agreeable with the rule of wisedome, by grant of the <hi>Toleration</hi> desired to prevent the decay of the one, and to incounter the rising and grouth of the other.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Besides, if a surcease of vrging Conformitie and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7942:16"/>Subscription be for curing the disease of partialitie and contention in the churches of this Kingdome altogether needfull: then can there not against the <hi>Toleration</hi> sollicited by vs any iust exception bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: the real vse and practise of the Lords Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in his publique worship for the guiding of his Churches being of as great necessitie, as the disvse and reiection of humane devises &amp; Romish Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities in the same. That the present Conformitie &amp; Subscription should in politique discourse and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son determine and not further be pressed, this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration doth admonish vs, namely, that whē the remedie, prepared to cure the disease of the State, doth in the application thereof augment and stren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the maladie, we ought to forbeare all further recourse to the said remedie. Of this nature and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect we finde the vrging of the said Conformitie &amp; Subscription to be. Wee are not ignorant that it is suggested vnto your Ma. that, for silencing of Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sensions in the Church, the silencing of Inconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitans is an admirable and present meane. But the observed experience of sundrie yeares vnder your Ma. and your predecessor <hi>Q. Elizabeth,</hi> doth witnes and proclayme to the world, that for freeing the Church from the sickenes of Division and Faction, the vrging of the said Conformitie is no receipt of any soveraine vertue in that behalfe. It hath (wee see) been often administred by the <hi>Prelats</hi> and their serviceable <hi>Apothecaries:</hi> but ever with no better succes then an vnseasonable Medicine, which doth exasperate and not temper the humors. As there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7942:16"/>Physicians doe <hi>plus interdum quiete quàm mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendo atque agendo proficere:</hi> so in the cure of infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and distempers of the State <hi>Connivere melius est, quàm intempestivis remedijs delicta accendere.</hi> The ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of <hi>Moecenas</hi> to <hi>Augustus</hi> is worthy the drawing into practise. It is (saieth he to the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror</hi>) a point of speciall wisedome, not to suffer <hi>new names,</hi> or ought from whence discord may arise. For by interteyning matter of partialitie &amp; discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment amongst the people on the parte of the Governors, as the parties wronged finding no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse, are easily inclined to decay in opiniō of their wisedome and affection towards them: so many advantages are offered to the common Adversarie, and sundrie opportunities of doing service to the State intercepted and lost. It can not be reputed a sufficient plea in the cause of pressing the present Conformitie and Subscription, to alleadge that the surceasing and the remove thereof is the abrogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that which is allowed by the State, and hath the force of a Law. For <hi>first</hi> the State doth not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the vse of the ceremonies as a Statute, prefixed to the booke of common Prayer &amp; Preface of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, but doeth tolerate them for the time. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> the Statute 13. <hi>Elizab.</hi> requireth Subscripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on so farre as concerneth the doctrine of Faith and Sacraments <hi>only:</hi> which, who refuseth? <hi>Thirdly,</hi> in case the said Ceremonies were inioyned by Law, yet out of a regarde to a publique benefite and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent necessitie, even good Lawes may, in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Politiks, suffer derogatiō: how much more
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7942:17"/>repelable then are such Constitutions, as authorise the vse of a scandalous and vnprofitable Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? If there were in the said Cōstitutions some be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite to the publique: yet if the inconvenience of the Law be greater then the fruite reaped thereby, the said Law may with honor to the Statute be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to discontinue and expire. And forasmuch as the inferior Law ought to give place vnto the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior: the Law of <hi>vnitie</hi> &amp; peace in the Churches being of a nobler discent and ranke, thē that of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Conformitie in humane Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: the Canon for the said Conformitie, in case it worke a disvnion in the cōfederate members of the Church, ought so farre to yeeld to the said Law of <hi>vnitie,</hi> as not to appeare or contest with it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> How agreable it is with the wisedome of a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Potentate to hold a course that will daunt the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of his State &amp; Religion, &amp; discourage them from practise &amp; attempt against the same, no Prince knoweth so accurately as your Ma. Now whether the said <hi>Toleratiō</hi> be not a course of this consequēce and power, it may please your High to dispute with your most noble self. The lesse hope your professed Adversaries shall discerne of subverting the Gospel and of re-advancing Poperie amongst vs, so much the more will they grow disharted and vnspirited for matter of proiect and conspiracie against your Person and Throne: But the more our Churches are purged from Romish Traditions &amp; Reliques, &amp; the more ground the Gospell winneth vpon Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ by the vigilant and carefull indeavours of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7942:17"/>Ministers thereof (two worthy effects accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the said Toleration) so much the lesse hope will the enimies of your Religion and State conceive of prevayling against the one and the other. And for that regarde if it shall vnder your royall approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and protection, be lawfull for vs to worship and honour the Lord Iesus according to the directions only left in his holy worde, and after the maner ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served in the reformed Churches, which have so farre proceeded in their Separation from <hi>Rome,</hi> that they hold with it no Communiō, either in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Doctrine of that Sea, or in the Constitution, Rites and Formalities of the same: we trust that the Lord Iesus, in the behalf of whose kingdome we are humble suters, will so honor this your Ma. grant of the said Toleration, that <hi>Antichrist</hi> with the whole partie of his favorits and adherents, will out of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire renounce and disclaime all further plotting &amp; attempting, either against the Kingdome of the Gospell or against your Crowne and Dignitie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
               <hi>If</hi> the defect of <hi>Toleration</hi> and the holding of the said course <hi>Prelaticall,</hi> bee a meane to abridge your Ma. in the number of your serviceable and faithfull Subiects (in the multitude of whom consisteth the strength and glorie of a Prince,<note place="margin">Proverb. 14 28.</note> and amongst whom the losse, even of one ought to bee precious in your sight) and withall to cast vpon the governement of the Churches of the Lord Iesus within this your Kingdome a double blemish and imputation, the one that it is fashioned not according to the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne shewed to the true Prophet in the mount, but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7942:18"/>according to the mould of the false Prophet sitting on the 7. hilles: the other that it holdeth a procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of much sharpnes and rigour aswell for the si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencing &amp; removing frō out the Church no meane number of the worthiest Pastors within this Lande, as for the disgracing and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raducing of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands otherwise of your Ma. most loyal and best af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Subiects in regarde of their affection to the Reformation desired. May it then please your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Ma. to draw vnder the examination of your most <hi>politique</hi> and <hi>religious</hi> thoughts, what wee doe here propounde, and to deliberate with your noble heart seriously and vnpartially, whether to prevent the inconveniences now particulated and charged vpon the said course <hi>Pontificall</hi> and the want of the said <hi>Toleration,</hi> it answere not the true principles of wisedome to cōdescend vnto our iust &amp; most due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Request: considering that it is enioyned to Princes by the Prince of Heaven &amp; earth, both to prize as a singular blessing the multitude of faithfull subiects, and so farre to regarde the honor of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name in the governement of his Churches, as not to give cause of publike obloquie and reproach thereto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If</hi> we shall impute to the defect of <hi>Toleration</hi> and to the said course <hi>Pontificall</hi> the Inconveniences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue remembred: we shall (wee truste) offer to the Prelats no wrong in that behalfe. For we doe alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die see that out of a care to worship the Lord accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his worde, and detestation to the rags &amp; ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Poperie (which are as yet with the scandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7942:18"/>of the Lords people and with the confirming of the Romanist in his love to a forrein <hi>Priest,</hi> &amp; in his disloyaltie to your Ma. reteined after a zealous sorte in our Churches) sundrie your High. Subiects have actually quitted the Realme. That many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vpon the same grounds do performe asmuch, some in wish and desire, some in purpose and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, is not improbable. That it is in the nature and reach of the said course held by the Prelats to strip your Ma. of the vse and service of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of your most affectionate and devoted Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, may hereby appeare, in that the Prelats have or pretend to have power of excōmunicating and imprisoning, not some few but all such as shal refuse the Oath <hi>ex officio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. 3.4.5.6.7.8 27.139.</note> disclayme Kneeling at the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, denie the Convocation to be the true repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentative Church of Christ within this Lande, give no allowance to al and every parte of the Leiturgy: withstand Conformitie and Subscription: affirme that the Ministers cannot yeeld to all these things with a good conscience, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> authoritie then of the said Prelats being of this extent, incase it should be drawen into executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on against so many of your Ma. Subiects, as are lya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their censures in regarde of the above named and supposed offences &amp; other transgressions iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable in their Courts: the holdes and prisons alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die designed within this Realme to the personal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint of delinquents, though they were for nūber doubled or trebled, yet would not be capable of so great a multitude, as should be sentenced thervnto.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7942:19"/>And doth not a Prisoner, during the time of his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonmēt, rest disabled for the service of his Prince? If for the tyme hee stand in the account of a persone vnserviceable and, as it were, dead to the Crowne and State: then if the said <hi>Pontificall</hi> course shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and without partialitie be executed, it will in a measure vnsufferable abridge your Ma. in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of your serviceable and loving Subiects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Touching</hi> the imputation and dishonor, whereto the regiment of the Churches of the Lord Iesus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst vs, is by the said course <hi>Prelaticall</hi> exposed: for the iustifying hereof wee appeale, first to the iudgement of all the reformed Churches in forrein parts: and secondly, to the Papists themselves. The reformed Churches, namely those who haue pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Lords publique worship from the polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Antichrist in farre greater measure then wee haue done, and are growē into an hatred of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vises and trash, cannot (if they wilbe trew to their owne principles, and sutable in their proceedings) but condemne for Romish &amp; Antichristian, what is from out the <hi>Synagogues</hi> of Priests and Iesuits trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported into the holy <hi>Congregations</hi> of our Saviour Christ: they cannot but deplore the indignitie and wronge offered to the Churches of God amongst vs, in the persons of those worthie and learned Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, who are for their love to Reformation, and for their vnconformitie to the rites and observances of Rome, silenced, deprived, and after an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie maner traduced and disgraced, yea in the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and intendement of the Canons <hi>excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:7942:19"/>and <hi>anathematized.</hi> they cannot but brande this proceeding with the marke of vnvsuall <hi>rigour,</hi> such as whereof no age can give an instance, as vsed by the true professors of the Gospell against their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and fellow-servants in the worke of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie, vpon this ground and pretext of the saide vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformitie. Thus must the reformed Churches charge and cēsure the said <hi>Prelaticall</hi> course, or passe sentence against them selves.</p>
            <p>And as for the <hi>Romanists:</hi> doe they not applaude the holding of the saide course by the Prelats? Is it not a matter of excellent contentement to their soules, that the <hi>Churchgovernement</hi> of Rome, &amp; sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie of the outward and proper <hi>Formalities</hi> thereof, should be honored in our Churches, &amp; the impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the same, and seekers of Reformation in this behalfe pursued with reproach, imprisonement, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, and ruine in their whole estate? If the <hi>Romanists</hi> the capitall enemies of your Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Crowne, and of the Gospell professed by your selfe and your Subiects, doe thus exalt and triumph in beholding the proceedings on the parte of our Prelats, for the support of the Romish church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement and the appendants thereto, and for the extirpation of such as sollicite the displanting &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move thereof: doth not this their triumphing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clayme to the world, aswel our readie and professed concurrence with them in their ecclesiasticall tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and regiment, as their approbation of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous measure and vexation offered vnto vs? And can there bee a greater reproach and imputation
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:7942:20"/>throwen vpon the Governement and Officers of our Churches, then that we should concurre both in the one and the other with the fashions of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon?</hi> that the one and the other should be condemned by the sincerest professors of <hi>Christ,</hi> and commended by the followers of <hi>Antichrist?</hi> censu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by our best <hi>friends,</hi> and approoved by our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test <hi>enemies?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If</hi> then the defect of <hi>Toleration</hi> and the holding of the said course <hi>Pontificall</hi> doe in the nature and reach of the <hi>Canons,</hi> in case they be really and vnpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially executed, aswell extraordinarily preiudice your Crowne and Dignitie in taking frō your Ma. the vse and service of so many thousands your most loyall Subiects, as expose the governement of the Churches vnder you to much imputation and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor. It may please you to remember how an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swereably your Ma. shall proceed to the Maxims of true Policy, in case you take order by the grant of the said <hi>Toleration,</hi> for the prevention &amp; redresse of the abovementioned inconveniences. Whereto we hope your Ma. wilbe the rather induced, when you shall consider that the best reformed Churches of Europe, interteyning in opinion and practise the cause for which we suffer, are by the Prelats, in our persons and through our sides wounded and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured with all reproach, yea pursued with suspensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, degradation, imprisonment, excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and anathemaes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hetherto</hi> we haue in all humilitie and reverence offered to your Princely view and consideration as
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:7942:20"/>pleading with your Ma. in favour of vs, two impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant arguments: <hi>the</hi> one shewing that the Church Cōstitution and governement sollicited by vs, doth better sort with your imperial Crowne then the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement of the Prelats: <hi>the</hi> other, that it standeth with the reason of State to allow the <hi>Toleration</hi> desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wee</hi> are now in the third and last place most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie to beseech your Ma. that you would vouchsafe to take notice of the vexation and rigorous measure offered vnto vs by the Prelats. Our purpose is not to enter into particularities, but to present your Ma. in briefe with a generall taste and view thereof, so farre as it may serve for some inducemēt to procure from your royall heart a commiseration of vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The indignities</hi> and wrongs we have received from the said Prelats are manifold and of an high nature. They have not spared to wrong vs in our Soules &amp; Consciences: in our Callings and Functions: in our Bodies: in our Goods and Livings: in our good Names and Credite: in our Writings and Discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, of which some they inlarge with additions for the gracing of their cause: some they shorten &amp; dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member for the concealing of the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The wrong</hi> we have received in our Soules &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, doth in parte discover it self hereby, in that some vpon vehement vrging on the parte of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops of Subscription and Conformitie, having in the end yeelded thereto, have within few dayes after vppon a more serious conference with their owne Conscience, discerning their errour and miscariage
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:7942:21"/>herein, languished vnto death. And wee doubt not but the present Subscribers and Conformers, when it shall please the Lord to shewe mercie to his poore Churches in honoring them with the libertie &amp; vse of his holy Ordinances, will then crye with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops of Asia: <hi>Nos non nostra voluntate, sed necessitate adducti subscripsimus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Evagr hist. lib. 3. cap. 9.</note>
               <hi>non animo sed verbis dunt axat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sensimus. Further,</hi> doe we not receive at the hands of our Prelats a deepe wound in our Soules, when they abridge vs in the libertie of searching the truth for the satisfying of our Conscience? This doe they, when they require vs to rest satisfied with the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Superiors, and menace Excommunication in the case of our refusall. <hi>This</hi> doe they, when they would enslave vs to Antichrist by enioyning vs to allow the Rites borrowed frō him:<note place="margin">Prov. 22.7.</note> and when they would subiect vs to the wil &amp; power of man, by pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing vs to admit in matters of religion, the <hi>bare</hi> wil &amp; pleasure of man, and to acknowledge in him, an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute power for the ordering of things sometime indifferent (in the number wherof the things in cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie are not) and for an vnproportionable distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of punishments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How</hi> iniurious they, the said Prelats are to vs in our Callings &amp; Functions, is not vnknowen at home or abroad. They assume vnto themselves the name of the Church, the power of ordination to the ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and the sole execution of censures: they exact fees in regard of these: they abādone vs to the check of every Offician and Sumner. Vpon our refusall to conforme or subscribe, they commande our appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:7942:21"/>in their Courts: they poste vs from one Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal to another: and from this Terme to the next succeeding. They tyre our bodyes and exhaust our purses And in the issue after wee have bin sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie harassed and loaded with cōtumelies, they silence vs and degrade vs from our Ministerie: they exact bonds of vs, whereby to restreyne vs from all further intermedling in the same: and lest the world should censure them for too much partialitie &amp; charitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, they passe vs over to Sathan by their thun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der-bolts of Excommunication.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> not contented with proceedings of this qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie against vs, they, the said Prelats by their Officers breake open the dores of our houses and chambers: they seaze vpon what pleaseth them: they dispatch vs to the <hi>Gate house,</hi> or the <hi>Clinke,</hi> there to endure an vnlimited imprisonment, hunger and cold, chaynes and fetters sometymes: there to be shopped vp for a tyme in such sorte (in case wee stirre the humor in them) as that we shall see neither friend nor foe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sunne nor Moone; and there likewise to spend our dayes &amp; last breathing (as some haue done) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse the Lord dispose their hearts to compassion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi> be thus wronged in our Soules, in our Callings, in our Bodyes, is a matter of surpassing indignitie &amp; griefe: considering the nature of the cause for which we suffer: and specially considering there hath been not long since published for triall of these cōtrover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies a most equall <hi>Offer of Disputation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">M. Iacobs booke. The Abridg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of the Ministers of Lincolne Dioces. Whitenhall. 12. Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Remooval. &amp;c.</note> which is no more answered by them, thē sundrie other our wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, which they passe over with silence. But yet
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:7942:22"/>they, the said Prelats, nothing regarding the same, &amp; being vnsatisfied with their afore-remembred iniu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stice and violence, take vp other proceedings against vs. They dispossesse and deprive vs of our free holds and livings: they expose vs, our wives and children to beggerie: they<note n="“" place="margin">Canō 76.</note> barre vs frō imploying our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and industrie otherwise for the interteynement of our families, not afoording vnto vs the favor of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, which at the dissolutiō of Monasteries, <hi>Monkes</hi> and <hi>Friers</hi> did finde amongst vs: and which Theeves and Murtherers may now enioy through the <hi>chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table bequests</hi> of the dead. Hereto if we shall adde the forme they hold in their courses against vs, their charitie towards vs will appeare the more cleerely. They presse vpon vs the taking of an<note n="*" place="margin">Magna charta. cap. 18.</note> vnlawful and irreligious Oath, such as is no where in vse, but in the Courts of popish inquisition: that we should fall to the accusation of our selfes, and to the detection of others, is a matter much affected by them: being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, they take vpon them notwithstanding to sitt in iudgement and to passe sentence against vs. They intercept and take from vs our possessions, not by the verdit of Iurors,<note place="margin">Magna char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta. cap. 29.</note> as the law hath appointed, but by the sole authoritie and voyce of one man: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the punishment they inflict exceed the offence in question they regarde not. The benefite of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale, which the law of<note n="a" place="margin">Fascicul. rer repetend in appellar. Parisiens. fol 34.</note> God, and each several Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alloweth, they<note n="b" place="margin">Canon. 98.</note> denye vnto vs. And bringing our cause before the civill Magistrate, lest he should yeeld vs reliefe, they change (at their pleasure) the warrants of our commitment.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:7942:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> lest we should in these discomforts and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities gather comfort vnto our selves from the consideration of the integritie of our cause &amp; of our indeavour to approove the cariage of our actions to the Christians amongst whom wee converse: they cast not on vs some light <hi>aspersion and blemish,</hi> but heape vpon vs the greatest imputations. To censure &amp; reproach vs for arrogancie and pride, for want of all good literature and knowledge, for men of facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and turbulent spirits, for Schismatickes and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans, is an ordinarie charitie we receiue from them, and such as being vncōpared with some other their calumniations of vs, might easilie without contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and grieving be passed over. But as if we were altogether vnworthie to treade vpon the earth, or to beholde the Sunne, and as if wee were compounded of impieties to God, and disloyalties to our Prince: they blush not to give forth that we plot the subver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the State and Church: that we are enemies to your Ma. Crowne and Soveraintie: <hi>that</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">B of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne in his answer to a Catholick gent. pag. 124.</note>
               <hi>wee in bookes and practise hold it for a point of divinitie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose Princes, surprise their persons, and renounce allege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance:</hi> that wee are worse then the antichristian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists. Whereat, namely this later calumny, we doe not much mervell: they and the Papists being of so neare an affinitie and correspondence. Herevpon it is that towards them, the said Prelats, either forbeare the execution of the Law, or they performe it in a cariage of all favorable mitigation &amp; temper: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in questions concerning vs, they proceed with all extremitie, yea without, beyond, and contrarie to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:7942:23"/>Law: they, the said Prelats being not able to shew by what Law of God or man, they dispatch vs to prison, or keepe vs vnder-restraint without limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at their pleasure, &amp; that sometimes in cold yrons and with threats of the rack. But here wee are not without this comfort in that your Excellent Ma. in your answere to <hi>Tortus,</hi> doth acknowledge our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines to the Oath of Supremacie:<note place="margin">B. of Lincol in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to a Catholike pag 142.</note> and the Bishop of Lincolne him selfe (so forcible is trueth) our loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie to your royall person.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore (most Noble, Mightie, and gracious Prince)</hi> sith these proceedings held against vs by the Prelats, are for the manifold indignities and oppression of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in them vnto vs, and in our persons to the best reformed Churches in Europe, such as doe iustly inforce vs with the dolefull cries of our distressed hearts to fill the eares both of God &amp; men, for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion towards vs and redresse: And sith wee have made it appeare vnto your Maiestie (as wee hope) that the governement and courses interteyned by the said Prelats, are not so compatible with your Scepter &amp; State, as the nature and forme of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement sollicited by vs: And sith likewise the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Maxims of Policie doe perswade and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant the grant of the favour wee doe desire: Let our humble Motion (most deare Soveraine) finde grace and regarde in your eyes: Let vs taste of that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cely commiseration, which in other nations and in all ages both Popish and Ethnick Potentats haue shewed to persons of our profession and qualitie. So shall your Maiestie highly honour your selfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:7942:23"/>God and the world, at home and abroade. All Protestant Churches shall reioyce at the hearing thereof, when they shall finde the Ordinances of Christ imbraced by them, to be countenanced and honoured by your Maiestie in our assemblies: their blessings, as the dew, shall fall vpon your Highnes &amp; your Posteritie. The heartes of those that sigh and grone vnder the burdē of the <hi>Prelacie,</hi> and who long to beholde the glorie and beautie of Christs King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, shall ever admire and blesse you. All such your Subiects, as haue separated from Rome &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the Gospell, shall make tender vnto you of a most worthie acknowledgement, when they shall see partiality and faction remooved from out the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Churches of this Lande: and in lieu thereof a cariage of mutuall amitie and respect interteined. The Prelats them selves shall be disburdened of that heavie weight of sinne against the Lord, of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall toyle, and of that great obloquie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, which at home and in forrein parts by their irregular and rigorous proceedings against their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low servants and brethren they doe frō time to time drawe vpon them. Finally, Christ Iesus (who wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth as King in the midst of his Churches) behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the mercie and compassion extended by you to his poore distressed and afflicted members, shall vouchsafe you the enioyance of the blessing desired by that good King <hi>Ezechias:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 39.8.</note> even <hi>Peace and truth in your Highnes dayes, and in the dayes of your posteritie for ever.</hi> Now the God of Heaven give vs favour in your eyes this day. The Lord multiplie vpon your
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:7942:24"/>royall selfe and your noble issue all honorable felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. The Lord disappoint the proiects and attempts of your enemies, AMEN.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ma. most loyall, faithfull and<lb/> obedient Subiect, some of the late<lb/> silenced and deprived Ministers<lb/> and people consenting in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<lb/> with them.</signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iob. 17.24.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Iudge not according to the appearance: but iudge righteous iudgement.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iob 6.25.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>How stedfast are the words of righteousnes? and what can any of you iustly reprove?</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iob 6.29.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Turne I pray you: let there be none iniquitie: returne I say: and you shall see yet my righteousnes in that behalfe. Is there ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie in my tongue? Doth not my mouth feele sorrowes?</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Math 22.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Giue vnto Casar the things which are Casars: and giue vnto God those things which are Gods.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Pag. 21. lin. 2. put out <hi>is.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7942:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>